<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<spec>
  <overview>
    <spec_id>arc-auditing-spec</spec_id>
    <spec_version>1</spec_version>
    <status>active</status>
    <source>
      <design_path>docs/plans/arc-auditing-spec/2026-04-22/design.md</design_path>
      <design_iteration>2026-04-22</design_iteration>
    </source>
    <title>Spec Auditing Skill</title>
    <description>
      Provide arcforge with a read-only, advisory-only audit skill for the SDD
      pipeline's upstream artifacts (design.md, spec.xml, details/, dag.yaml).
      The skill fills a gap documented in
      docs/research/sdd-v2-downstream-contract-gap.md: SDD v2's existing
      validation points are binary block-or-pass, leaving no channel for
      "notify the human, let them decide" feedback. arc-auditing-spec fans out
      three axis-aligned sub-agents, presents structured findings via
      AskUserQuestion U3 two-stage triage, and surrenders final decisions to
      the main session — never modifying upstream artifacts itself.
    </description>
    <scope>
      <includes>
        <feature id="skill-contract">Public contract of the /arc-auditing-spec skill: user-invoked invocation semantics, hard read-only boundaries enforced via tool grants, no pipeline auto-invocation, implementation delegated to arc-writing-skills.</feature>
        <feature id="audit-agents">Three parallel fan-out sub-agents (cross-artifact-alignment, internal-consistency, state-transition-integrity), their finding schema, axis-scope separation, and graceful degradation on missing inputs.</feature>
        <feature id="output-and-interaction">Markdown-table report format, U3 two-stage AskUserQuestion triage UX (multiSelect Stage 1, batched Stage 2 with diff previews), Decisions table output, and optional L4-path persistence via --save flag.</feature>
      </includes>
      <excludes>
        <reason>Pipeline auto-invocation — brainstorming / refining / planning MUST remain unchanged; the skill is ad-hoc user-invoked (T1 decision).</reason>
        <reason>Autonomous edits — reviewer agents never modify audited artifacts; post-audit execution belongs to the main session.</reason>
        <reason>Code review / PR review — source-code review is handled by arc-requesting-review, arc-receiving-review, Claude Code /review, pr-review-toolkit; this skill only audits spec-family artifacts.</reason>
        <reason>Cross-spec batch audit — one invocation audits one spec-id; multi-spec loops are user-driven, not built in.</reason>
        <reason>Policy boundary around free-text edits to structured artifacts (Finding 2.5 in the gap report) — deferred to a separate future spec (arc-structured-artifact-policy).</reason>
        <reason>Coordinator / engine bug fixes — A3 agent surfaces DAG state drift, but fixes to scripts/lib/coordinator.js belong to a separate engine-fix spec.</reason>
        <reason>Changes to upstream pipeline skills — arc-brainstorming / arc-refining / arc-planning and their Iron Laws are not touched by this spec.</reason>
      </excludes>
    </scope>
  </overview>

  <details>
    <detail_file path="details/skill-contract.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/audit-agents.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/output-and-interaction.xml" />
  </details>
</spec>
