<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="coordinator-commits">
  <title>Coordinator Commit-Integration and Cleanup Scope</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>scripts/lib/coordinator.js (specifically _mergeEpicsInBase at coordinator.js:426-493 and cleanupWorktrees at coordinator.js:501-538)</artifact>
    <artifact>scripts/lib/models.js (TaskStatus enum and dag epic schema)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>Modified scripts/lib/coordinator.js with dag.yaml staging inside _mergeEpicsInBase and pure-disk cleanup</artifact>
    <artifact>Modified scripts/cli.js with --epic flag on the cleanup subcommand</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-001">
    <title>Integrate commit carries dag.yaml state transition</title>
    <description>
      The coordinator's _mergeEpicsInBase MUST bundle dag.yaml state changes
      into the integrate commit it produces. Both epic.status = COMPLETED and
      epic.worktree = null MUST be mutated in the same in-memory save, and
      specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST be staged with git add before the
      integrate commit is created. This closes the §2.2 / §6.1 defect where
      dag.yaml writes persisted as dirty working-tree state across sessions.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-001-ac1">
        Given a spec with one or more epics in status=completed awaiting merge,
        When arcforge merge runs and _mergeEpicsInBase processes an epic,
        Then the in-memory dag mutation MUST set both epic.status = COMPLETED
        and epic.worktree = null in the same save operation.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 1 (Q1=c resolution)</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-001-ac2">
        Given _mergeEpicsInBase has produced the mutated dag.yaml on disk,
        When the integrate commit is created,
        Then git add specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST be invoked before the
        commit so that git log -1 --name-only on the integrate commit
        includes specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R1.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-001-ac3">
        Given an integrate commit produced by _mergeEpicsInBase,
        When its message is inspected,
        Then the subject MUST remain feat: integrate &lt;epic&gt; epic (no
        separate chore commit for the dag.yaml update), and the commit MUST
        include both the files merged from the epic branch and the dag.yaml
        state change as a single logical unit.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-001-ac4">
        Given arcforge merge completes successfully for an epic,
        When git status is read immediately after,
        Then specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST NOT appear in the working-tree
        diff (no M flag), confirming that the coordinator has left no
        uncommitted drift behind.
        <trace>design.md §Problem — §2.2 / §6.1 resolution</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-002">
    <title>cleanup is a pure disk-and-branch operation</title>
    <description>
      arcforge cleanup MUST NOT mutate specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml under any
      code path. With fr-cc-001 transferring worktree=null into the merge
      commit, cleanup's only responsibilities are filesystem removal, git
      worktree prune, and local branch deletion for fully-merged branches.
      This removes the drift window that previously existed between cleanup
      and any subsequent user action.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-002-ac1">
        Given cleanup is invoked for one or more completed epics,
        When the operation returns,
        Then specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST be byte-identical to its state
        before the cleanup invocation (no write, no git add, no diff in git
        status).
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 1 (cleanup purified)</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-002-ac2">
        Given cleanup processes an epic whose worktree directory exists on
        disk,
        When cleanup runs,
        Then it MUST remove the worktree directory via fs.rmSync AND invoke
        git worktree prune so the git worktree registry no longer references
        the removed path.
        <trace>design.md §Problem — §7.2 cleanup scope</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-003">
    <title>cleanup deletes fully-merged epic branches</title>
    <description>
      arcforge cleanup MUST extend its scope to local branch deletion. For
      every epic it processes, cleanup MUST attempt git branch -d
      &lt;epic-branch&gt; and MUST succeed silently when the branch is
      fully-merged to the current branch, MUST skip silently when the branch
      is not fully-merged (no -D force-delete), and MUST surface per-branch
      results in the command output.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-003-ac1">
        Given an epic whose branch has been fully merged into the current
        branch,
        When cleanup processes that epic,
        Then the branch MUST be removed via git branch -d and the branch
        name MUST appear in the cleanup JSON result under a removed-branches
        listing.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R1.2</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-003-ac2">
        Given an epic whose branch has uncommitted changes or is not merged
        into the current branch,
        When cleanup processes that epic,
        Then the branch MUST be left intact (no git branch -D, no force),
        MUST NOT cause the overall cleanup invocation to fail, and MUST be
        surfaced in the cleanup JSON result under a skipped-branches listing.
        <trace>design.md §Problem — §7.2(a) branch cleanup gap</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-003-ac3">
        Given a cleanup invocation that removes N worktrees,
        When the cleanup command completes,
        Then the JSON output MUST list the worktrees removed and, as a
        separate field, the branches removed versus skipped, so that
        downstream automation can distinguish the two outcomes.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 1</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-004">
    <title>cleanup CLI exposes --epic flag consistent with expand and loop</title>
    <description>
      The CLI surface for cleanup MUST accept a --epic &lt;name&gt; flag to
      select a single epic, aligning with expand --epic and loop --epic. The
      existing positional [epic_ids...] form MUST remain functional as an
      alias. Skills SHOULD use the flag form going forward; positional form
      is retained solely for backward compatibility with existing
      invocations.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-004-ac1">
        Given a user or skill invokes arcforge cleanup --spec-id &lt;id&gt; --epic
        &lt;name&gt;,
        When the command parses arguments,
        Then it MUST target only the named epic within the given spec and
        MUST produce the same result shape as an equivalent positional
        invocation arcforge cleanup --spec-id &lt;id&gt; &lt;name&gt;.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R1.2 (Q3=a)</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-004-ac2">
        Given the arcforge CLI help output,
        When scripts/cli.js is invoked with --help or its usage banner
        printed,
        Then the cleanup usage line MUST list both the positional
        [epic_ids...] form and the --epic &lt;name&gt; flag form.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-004-ac3">
        Given arcforge cleanup is invoked with both positional epic ids and
        the --epic flag,
        When the CLI parses arguments,
        Then it MUST error with a clear message that the two forms are
        mutually exclusive, rather than silently preferring one over the
        other.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 1</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
