<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="skill-hooks">
  <title>Skill-Level Hooks into arcforge finish</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>skills/arc-finishing-epic/SKILL.md (Step 4 Option 1 merge locally path)</artifact>
    <artifact>skills/arc-dispatching-teammates/SKILL.md and references/wrap-up-sequence.md (Step 8 wrap-up)</artifact>
    <artifact>skills/arc-coordinating/SKILL.md (command table)</artifact>
    <artifact>evals/scenarios/ (new scenarios covering each skill hook)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>Modified SKILL.md files with finish --if-last calls at the correct step</artifact>
    <artifact>New eval scenarios for sdd-downstream-contract skill hooks (naming: evals/scenarios/sdd-downstream-contract-*.md)</artifact>
    <artifact>Updated Red Flags / Common Rationalizations tables that close skip-finish loopholes</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-sh-001">
    <title>arc-finishing-epic Step 4 Option 1 calls finish --if-last</title>
    <description>
      skills/arc-finishing-epic/SKILL.md Step 4 Option 1 (merge locally)
      MUST be updated so that after the cleanup call on line 103 it invokes
      arcforge finish --spec-id &lt;spec-id&gt; --if-last. This is the single
      hook that makes Convention C automatic for the most common
      per-epic-terminus path (arc-implementing, arc-agent-driven, arc-
      looping, arc-dispatching-parallel all route through here).
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-001-ac1">
        Given skills/arc-finishing-epic/SKILL.md after implementation,
        When Step 4 Option 1 (Merge Locally) is read top-to-bottom,
        Then immediately after the finish-epic.js cleanup invocation
        currently at line 103 there MUST appear a line invoking arcforge
        finish --spec-id &lt;spec-id&gt; --if-last (or an equivalent
        finish-epic.js wrapper that forwards to the same CLI).
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-001-ac2">
        Given an agent session that has just merged the final epic of a
        sprint via arc-finishing-epic Step 4 Option 1,
        When the session completes,
        Then specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST have been removed and a
        chore(specs): finish &lt;spec-id&gt; sprint commit MUST be present on
        the current branch, evidencing that the skill hook fired.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.1 (end-to-end)</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-001-ac3">
        Given an agent session that merges a non-final epic,
        When the session completes,
        Then the --if-last call MUST have exited zero with no-op output and
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST still exist, so that intermediate
        epic merges do not accidentally delete planner output.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 2 (conditional)</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-sh-002">
    <title>arc-finishing-epic Step 4 Option 2 (PR) must not call finish</title>
    <description>
      skills/arc-finishing-epic/SKILL.md Step 4 Option 2 (Create PR) MUST
      NOT include any arcforge finish call. PRs land on the remote after
      human / CI review; local arcforge finish would fail its "all
      branches fully merged" guard. Users running PR-only sprints invoke
      arcforge finish manually after all PRs merge. The skill MUST
      document this in prose so the implementer does not insert finish by
      symmetry with Option 1.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-002-ac1">
        Given skills/arc-finishing-epic/SKILL.md after implementation,
        When Step 4 Option 2 is read,
        Then no line in that option MUST invoke arcforge finish (or a
        wrapper that forwards to it) under any conditional.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.1 (PR carve-out)</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-002-ac2">
        Given the same SKILL.md,
        When the reader reaches the end of Step 4 Option 2,
        Then prose MUST explain why PR-path does not auto-finish (guard
        mismatch, remote merge timing), and MUST direct the user to run
        arcforge finish manually once all PRs merge.
        <trace>design.md §Scope — Excludes (PR-based sprint-end)</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-sh-003">
    <title>arc-dispatching-teammates wrap-up calls finish --if-last</title>
    <description>
      skills/arc-dispatching-teammates/SKILL.md (Step 8b in the body or
      references/wrap-up-sequence.md, whichever is the authoritative
      location for the wrap-up prescription) MUST be updated so that after
      the batch arcforge cleanup call it invokes arcforge finish --spec-id
      &lt;spec-id&gt; --if-last. The lead session has the global view; this
      hook covers the multi-teammate dispatch scenario where per-teammate
      arc-finishing-epic cannot reliably detect "last epic" because
      teammates run in parallel.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-003-ac1">
        Given the authoritative wrap-up location in arc-dispatching-
        teammates after implementation,
        When Step 8 (wrap-up) is read top-to-bottom,
        Then immediately after the batch cleanup call there MUST appear a
        line invoking arcforge finish --spec-id &lt;spec-id&gt; --if-last.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.2 (Q4-2=b)</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-003-ac2">
        Given a lead session that dispatched multiple teammates, all of
        whom merged their final-sprint epics,
        When the lead session runs Step 8 wrap-up,
        Then specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml MUST be removed and the finish
        commit MUST be present on the lead's branch, evidencing that the
        lead-side hook fired rather than any individual teammate.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 2 (lead detects last)</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-sh-004">
    <title>arc-coordinating command table lists finish</title>
    <description>
      skills/arc-coordinating/SKILL.md command table MUST add a row for
      finish with the description "End a sprint (delete dag.yaml + epics/
      when all epics completed)" and example invocation arcforge finish
      --spec-id &lt;id&gt;. This makes the new subcommand discoverable through
      the same routing surface users already use to learn cleanup,
      expand, merge, sync, and status.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-004-ac1">
        Given skills/arc-coordinating/SKILL.md after implementation,
        When the command table near line 32 is read,
        Then a finish row MUST be present with the description noted
        above and an example arcforge finish --spec-id &lt;id&gt;.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-004-ac2">
        Given the same SKILL.md,
        When the full document is read for consistency,
        Then no claim MUST remain that cleanup removes dag.yaml or
        epics/ (earlier prose that conflated the two scopes MUST be
        updated so cleanup and finish are clearly separated).
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 3</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-sh-005">
    <title>Skill Red Flags close skip-finish rationalizations</title>
    <description>
      Each of the three modified SKILL.md files (arc-finishing-epic,
      arc-dispatching-teammates, arc-coordinating) MUST include at least
      one Red Flag entry (or Common Rationalizations row where that
      structure is used) that explicitly closes the loophole of skipping
      finish when it is the last epic. Phrasings MUST name concrete
      temptations ("This is the last epic but I will just git rm manually"
      / "finish seems redundant with cleanup"), not vague prohibitions.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-005-ac1">
        Given each of the three modified SKILL.md files,
        When its Red Flags / Common Rationalizations section is read,
        Then at least one entry MUST explicitly warn against manually
        performing git rm of dag.yaml / epics in place of calling finish,
        and MUST state that Convention C is the single sanctioned terminus
        path.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.4</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-005-ac2">
        Given an adversarial eval scenario that presents a last-epic merge
        and tempts the skill to skip finish (with a plausible-sounding
        rationalization),
        When the skill runs with the updated Red Flags in place,
        Then the agent MUST either invoke arcforge finish --if-last or
        surface the temptation and refuse it, and MUST NOT manually git
        rm dag.yaml / epics.
        <trace>design.md §Identifiable Requirements R2.4 (adversarial eval)</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-sh-006">
    <title>Skill-layer changes follow arc-writing-skills TDD-for-docs</title>
    <description>
      The implementation of fr-sh-001 through fr-sh-005 MUST proceed under
      arc-writing-skills discipline: RED (eval scenarios fail without the
      skill edits) → GREEN (skill edits land, scenarios pass) → REFACTOR
      (Red Flags / Rationalizations added to close remaining loopholes
      observed during REFACTOR). Each of the three skills modified MUST
      have at least one eval scenario under
      evals/scenarios/sdd-downstream-contract-*.md whose RED baseline is
      recorded and whose GREEN pass is verified in the implementing PR.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-006-ac1">
        Given the sdd-downstream-contract implementation PR,
        When the PR description and eval outputs are reviewed,
        Then at least three eval scenarios MUST be present (one per
        modified skill) each with a RED baseline evidencing pre-change
        failure and a GREEN result evidencing post-change success.
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 3 discipline</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-sh-006-ac2">
        Given the three modified SKILL.md files,
        When tests/skills/ pytest runs against them,
        Then every existing validator MUST continue to pass (no
        frontmatter regressions, no missing required sections, no word-
        count tier violations beyond the established limits).
        <trace>design.md §Proposed Solution — Layer 3 discipline</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
