<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="brainstorming">
  <title>Stage 1 — Brainstorming (Elicit)</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>specs/*/spec.xml (scan for existing spec_ids)</artifact>
    <artifact>specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml (when iterating an existing spec)</artifact>
    <artifact>docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/*/design.md (when iterating, reads previous iterations)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;date&gt;/design.md</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-001">
    <title>Scan Existing Specs Before Starting</title>
    <description>
      Brainstorming MUST scan the specs/ directory for existing spec_ids before
      beginning any elicitation, to detect potential iteration scenarios.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-001-ac1">
        Given a specs/ directory containing specs/auth/spec.xml and specs/payments/spec.xml,
        brainstorming MUST present both spec_ids (auth, payments) to the user before proceeding.
        <trace>REQ-F001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-001-ac2">
        Given an empty specs/ directory, brainstorming MUST proceed directly to
        new-spec flow without presenting any existing spec_ids.
        <trace>REQ-F001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-002">
    <title>Confirm Spec Target (New or Iteration)</title>
    <description>
      After scanning, brainstorming MUST ask the user to confirm whether this is
      a new spec or an iteration on an existing spec. The confirmation determines
      which conditional sections appear in the design doc output — it does not
      invoke a separate code path or "mode". Brainstorming has one behavior with
      context-sensitive output.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-002-ac1">
        Given a similar spec found, brainstorming MUST ask: "Iterating on &lt;spec-id&gt;
        (v&lt;N&gt; active)?" and wait for user confirmation before proceeding.
        <trace>REQ-F002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-002-ac2">
        Given no matching spec, brainstorming MUST propose a spec-id and ask:
        "New topic — proposed spec-id: &lt;suggestion&gt;. OK?" before proceeding.
        <trace>REQ-F002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-002-ac3">
        Brainstorming MUST NOT assume the target without user confirmation. The
        confirmation is explicit, not inferred.
        <trace>REQ-F002</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-003">
    <title>Output Format When No Prior Spec Exists</title>
    <description>
      When no prior spec.xml exists for the target spec-id, brainstorming produces
      a complete design doc at the canonical location. The refiner consumes the
      entire design doc — no structured delta section is needed because there is
      nothing prior to compare against.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-003-ac1">
        Output MUST be written to docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;YYYY-MM-DD&gt;/design.md.
        <trace>REQ-F003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-003-ac2">
        The design doc MUST contain substantive design content: problem description,
        proposed solution, identifiable requirements (in prose), and scope
        (what's included and excluded).
        <trace>REQ-F003</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-004">
    <title>Read Prior Spec and Iteration History Before Eliciting a Change</title>
    <description>
      When iterating on an existing spec, brainstorming MUST read the prior
      spec.xml and all previous design iterations before eliciting the change
      from the user. This ensures the change intent is informed by accurate
      current state, not by user recollection.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-004-ac1">
        Given specs/my-feature/spec.xml at v2, brainstorming MUST read the
        spec.xml content during Phase 1 (Understanding) before asking the user
        about changes.
        <trace>REQ-F004</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-004-ac2">
        Given two previous iterations (2026-01-01, 2026-03-15), brainstorming MUST
        read both design docs to understand the evolution history.
        <trace>REQ-F004</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-005">
    <title>Output Format When Prior Spec Exists</title>
    <description>
      When iterating on an existing spec, brainstorming produces a design doc
      whose primary content is a Context summary + natural-language Change Intent.
      The refiner reads this design doc alongside the existing spec.xml and
      derives the structured &lt;delta&gt; itself — no explicit delta section is
      authored in the design doc.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-005-ac1">
        The design doc MUST include a Context section summarizing the current
        spec scope in 2-3 sentences, with a reference to the spec.xml version.
        <trace>REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-005-ac2">
        The design doc MUST include a Change Intent section describing what is
        changing and why. This is the primary input for the refiner to derive
        the delta.
        <trace>REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-005-ac3">
        The design doc SHOULD include an Architecture Impact section describing
        how changes interact with existing design. Optional for simple changes.
        <trace>REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-005-ac4">
        The design doc MUST NOT include a pre-authored structured delta section
        (no explicit ADDED/MODIFIED/REMOVED lists). The LLM-based refiner
        performs the diff; the design doc carries only human-authored narrative
        intent.
        <trace>REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-006">
    <title>Spec ID Derivation and Confirmation</title>
    <description>
      When no prior spec exists, the spec_id MUST be derived from content at the
      end of Phase 2 (when scope is clear) and confirmed by the user before
      output. For iterations, the spec_id is inherited from the prior spec — no
      derivation step is needed.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-006-ac1">
        The spec_id MUST NOT be finalized before Phase 2 completes.
        <trace>REQ-F006</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-006-ac2">
        The user MUST explicitly confirm or modify the proposed spec_id before the
        design doc is written.
        <trace>REQ-F006</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-007">
    <title>Output Validation — Design Doc Structure</title>
    <description>
      Before writing the design doc to disk, brainstorming MUST validate that
      it conforms to the design doc contract (fr-cc-if-001).
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-007-ac1">
        When no prior spec exists, output MUST be validated as follows: file
        path follows docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;YYYY-MM-DD&gt;/design.md
        convention, design doc has substantive content (not empty/stub),
        identifiable requirements and scope present in prose. ERROR on any
        missing element.
        <trace>REQ-F003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-007-ac2">
        When a prior spec exists, output MUST be validated as follows: Context
        section present (with spec version reference), Change Intent section
        present, no pre-authored structured delta section. ERROR on missing
        required sections.
        <trace>REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-008">
    <title>Phase 0 — Pending-Conflict Detection and Iterate-Branch Auto-Entry</title>
    <description>
      Brainstorming's Phase 0 scan-and-route logic MUST check for the
      presence of specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md (the ephemeral
      handoff written by refiner per fr-rf-015 on R3 axis-1/2/3 block). If
      the file exists, brainstorming MUST automatically enter its iterate
      branch with the conflict body as Change Intent seed — the user does
      not need to retell the conflict. The user picks a candidate resolution
      (or describes their own); brainstorming writes a new dated
      docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;NEW-DATE&gt;/design.md with the
      resolution baked in; the pending file MUST be deleted on successful
      design write so zero authoritative state remains across the conflict
      cycle (R3 holds — refiner never wrote design.md; brainstorming did,
      after user authorization; the ephemeral marker existed transiently
      and is now removed).
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-008-ac1">
        Given specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md exists at the start
        of brainstorming Phase 0, brainstorming MUST automatically enter the
        iterate branch (without asking the user "new spec or iteration?") and
        load the file's conflict_description, candidate_resolutions, and
        cited design line ranges / Q&amp;A q_ids as Change Intent seed.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-008-ac2">
        Brainstorming MUST present the candidate resolutions to the user
        verbatim from the pending file and prompt for selection ("pick (a),
        (b), (c), or describe your own"). The user does not retell the
        conflict; brainstorming does not re-derive the conflict from
        scratch.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-008-ac3">
        Once the user selects (or describes) a resolution and brainstorming
        successfully writes the new design.md to
        docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;NEW-DATE&gt;/design.md, brainstorming
        MUST delete specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md. If the
        new-design write fails, the pending file MUST NOT be deleted —
        cleanup is gated on successful write.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-008-ac4">
        Brainstorming's Phase 0 conflict-detection branch MUST NOT modify or
        rewrite the _pending-conflict.md content — the file is read-only
        from brainstorming's perspective. Any changes to the conflict
        framing happen in the new design.md, not by editing the handoff
        file.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.3</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-bs-009">
    <title>Structured Decision-Log Output Format</title>
    <description>
      Brainstorming Phase 2 (eliciting Q&amp;A) MUST emit the Q&amp;A history
      as a structured decision-log conforming to fr-cc-if-008. The
      decision-log is consumed by refiner for Phase 4 axis 2 contradiction
      check (design ↔ Q&amp;A) and Phase 6 mechanical authorization check
      (axis 3 trace verification). The previous free-form decision-log.md
      format (where rows had no stable identifiers and refiner could not
      mechanically iterate over Q&amp;A rows by q_id) is replaced by the
      structured format.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-009-ac1">
        Each Q&amp;A row in the decision-log MUST carry the four required
        fields per fr-cc-if-008: q_id (stable identifier, unique per
        brainstorming session), question (verbatim text of the question
        asked), user_answer_verbatim (verbatim text of the user's answer),
        and deferral_signal (boolean — true when the answer matches
        deferral phrases like "use defaults", "covered.", "skip", "you
        decide", or similar; false otherwise).
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-009-ac2">
        The decision-log MUST be machine-parseable per fr-cc-if-008. The
        wire format (YAML, strict markdown table, etc.) is an
        implementation choice that brainstorming's writer and refiner's
        parser MUST agree on; the contract this requirement captures is
        the field shape and machine-parseability, not the format.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-009-ac3">
        q_id values MUST be stable across the brainstorming session — if
        a question is asked once, its q_id MUST NOT change in later
        revisions of the same decision-log within the same session. This
        stability is what enables refiner's traces (per fr-rf-010-ac5) to
        cite Q&amp;A rows by q_id and have those traces remain valid.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-bs-009-ac4">
        Brainstorming MUST detect deferral signals canonically: at minimum
        the phrases "use defaults", "covered.", "skip", "you decide" set
        deferral_signal=true. Implementations MAY extend the canonical
        list with additional deferral phrases, provided the extensions are
        documented alongside the format implementation.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
