<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="cross-cutting">
  <title>Cross-Cutting Rules, Interface Contracts, and Non-Functional Requirements</title>

  <!-- ═══════════════ Foundational Rules ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="fr-cc-001">
    <title>R1 — Human Consent for Raw Source</title>
    <description>
      Design docs (raw source) MUST NOT be created or modified without human
      consent or initiation. The LLM assists in elicitation but the human
      controls when a design doc is committed.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-001-ac1">
        A design doc MUST NOT be written to disk until the user explicitly confirms
        the content (e.g., "looks good", "commit it", section-by-section approval).
        <trace>REQ-F024</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-001-ac2">
        After a design doc is committed, it MUST NOT be modified. Any change
        requires a new iteration (new date folder, new design.md).
        <trace>REQ-F024</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-002">
    <title>R2 — Unidirectional Flow</title>
    <description>
      Downstream stages MUST NOT modify upstream artifacts. Refiner cannot modify
      design docs; planner cannot modify spec.xml.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-002-ac1">
        Refiner MUST NOT write to any file under docs/plans/. Its only
        output path on success is specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/. On block, refiner
        writes no files anywhere — the error is reported to terminal and
        refiner exits non-zero (per fr-rf-001-ac3).
        <trace>REQ-F025</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-002-ac2">
        Planner MUST NOT write to specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml or
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/details/. Its only output paths are
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml and specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/epics/.
        <trace>REQ-F025</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <!-- ═══════════════ Pipeline Interface Contracts ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-001">
    <title>Design Doc Contract</title>
    <description>
      The design doc is the complete output of brainstorming and the complete
      input to the refiner. The refiner consumes the entire design doc — no
      special section or structured summary is needed. This contract defines
      the design doc structure with context-sensitive sections: when no prior
      spec exists, the doc carries full problem/solution/requirements/scope in
      prose; when a prior spec exists, the doc carries Context + Change Intent.
      There are no modes — one design doc structure with conditional sections.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-001-ac1">
        Design docs MUST be located at docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;YYYY-MM-DD&gt;/design.md.
        The spec-id is derived from the directory name. The iteration date is
        derived from the date directory name.
        <trace>REQ-F003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-001-ac2">
        When no prior spec exists for this spec-id, the design doc MUST
        contain substantive design content: at minimum, a description of the
        problem, proposed solution, and identifiable requirements (in prose).
        Empty or stub design docs are ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-001-ac3">
        When a prior spec exists for this spec-id, the design doc MUST include
        at minimum: a Context section (summarizing current spec state with
        version reference) and a Change Intent section (describing what is
        changing and why). Missing Context or Change Intent is ERROR. A
        pre-authored structured delta section (ADDED/MODIFIED/REMOVED lists)
        MUST NOT appear — the refiner derives the delta from narrative intent.
        <trace>REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-001-ac4">
        The refiner determines which conditional sections to expect from
        filesystem state, not from fields in the design doc:
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml exists → expect Context + Change Intent;
        does not exist → expect prose with problem/solution/requirements/scope.
        This is a single-behavior filesystem check, not a mode selector.
        <trace>REQ-F003, REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-002">
    <title>Spec Identity Header Contract</title>
    <description>
      The spec.xml identity header is the interface contract between refiner
      (producer) and planner (consumer). This is the single source of truth
      for the header format.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-002-ac1">
        Identity header MUST contain: spec_id (string), spec_version (positive
        integer), status ("active"), source/design_path (valid file path),
        source/design_iteration (YYYY-MM-DD). Missing fields are ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-002-ac2">
        source/design_path MUST point to an existing design doc file. A path
        pointing to a non-existent file is ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-002-ac3">
        scope MUST list included features with IDs and excluded items with
        reasons. Empty scope is WARNING.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-002-ac4">
        When spec_version > 1, supersedes MUST be set to
        "&lt;spec-id&gt;:v&lt;previous-version&gt;". Missing supersedes for v2+ is ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <!-- ═══════════════ Contract Implementation Mechanism ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-003">
    <title>SDD Schemas (Guidance Layer)</title>
    <description>
      Each pipeline artifact MUST have a corresponding schema file in
      scripts/lib/sdd-schemas/ that serves as the format guide for LLMs.
      Schema files are the guidance layer — they tell the LLM what format
      to produce. They live in scripts/lib/ (shared infrastructure) so any
      skill can read them without cross-skill coupling. Full schema content
      definitions are in details/sdd-schemas.xml (fr-sd-001 through fr-sd-007).
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-003-ac1">
        scripts/lib/sdd-schemas/design.md MUST exist and conform to the
        design doc schema definition (fr-sd-001 through fr-sd-004).
        <trace>REQ-F003, REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-003-ac2">
        scripts/lib/sdd-schemas/spec.md MUST exist and conform to the
        spec identity header schema definition (fr-sd-005 through fr-sd-007).
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-003-ac3">
        Schema files are the guidance layer only. They MUST NOT be the
        enforcement mechanism — enforcement is delegated to sdd-utils.js
        (fr-cc-if-004).
        <trace>REQ-F008</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-004">
    <title>SDD Utils (Validation Toolkit)</title>
    <description>
      Deterministic validation and information checks MUST be implemented in
      scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js. This module is a validation toolkit — it
      validates structure and provides information, but does NOT merge or
      author spec content (the LLM manages spec content directly, like
      maintaining a wiki page). Full API definitions are in
      details/sdd-schemas.xml (fr-sd-008, fr-sd-009). LLM judgment is
      reserved for semantic checks (contradictions, ambiguity).
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-004-ac1">
        sdd-utils.js MUST export the design doc validator API defined in
        fr-sd-008 (parseDesignDoc, validateDesignDoc).
        <trace>REQ-F003, REQ-F005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-004-ac2">
        sdd-utils.js MUST export the spec header validator API defined in
        fr-sd-009 (parseSpecHeader, validateSpecHeader).
        <trace>REQ-F010, REQ-F016</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-004-ac3">
        Semantic checks NOT implemented by this module (delegated to LLM):
        contradiction detection between requirements, ambiguity assessment,
        scope completeness judgment.
        <trace>REQ-F008, REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-004-ac4">
        When a schema file (fr-cc-if-003) and sdd-utils.js disagree on
        what is valid, sdd-utils.js wins. Schema files guide production;
        sdd-utils.js enforces correctness.
        <trace>REQ-F003, REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-005">
    <title>Skill Access Pattern</title>
    <description>
      Each pipeline skill accesses the contract through two layers:
      scripts/lib/sdd-schemas/ for format guidance (what to produce) and
      scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js for programmatic validation (is it correct).
      Both layers are shared infrastructure. No skill reads another skill's
      files.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-005-ac1">
        arc-brainstorming SKILL.md MUST invoke scripts/lib/print-schema.js
        (with target "design") before producing the design doc, to obtain
        the canonical schema derived from DESIGN_DOC_RULES. The skill MUST
        NOT embed a structural template for the design doc — structural
        content is schema, and schema has a single source (fr-sd-010,
        fr-sd-011).
        <trace>REQ-F003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-005-ac2">
        arc-refining SKILL.md MUST invoke scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js
        validateDesignDoc() for deterministic input validation before any
        formalization. If valid is false with ERROR issues, refiner MUST
        block per fr-rf-001-ac3 — print the issues to terminal, exit
        non-zero, and write no files (no refiner-report.md, no spec.xml).
        <trace>REQ-F008</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-005-ac3">
        arc-refining SKILL.md MUST invoke scripts/lib/print-schema.js
        (with target "spec") when producing spec.xml, and MUST invoke
        scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js validateSpecHeader() for deterministic
        output validation. If valid is false, refiner MUST NOT write any
        files. The skill MUST NOT embed a structural template for the
        spec header — structural content comes from the CLI and the
        exported SPEC_HEADER_RULES constant.
        <trace>REQ-F010, REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-005-ac4">
        arc-planning SKILL.md MUST invoke scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js
        validateSpecHeader() for spec.xml input validation before any
        decomposition. Planner MUST NOT read the design doc — it works
        from the spec only. Rationale: the three-layer model requires
        that the derived layer (DAG) reads only from the wiki layer
        (spec), never from the raw source layer (design doc). The spec's
        &lt;delta&gt; metadata provides the planning scope that would
        otherwise require reading the design doc.
        <trace>REQ-F016</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-006">
    <title>Validation Toolkit API Self-Documentation</title>
    <description>
      The exported function signatures of scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js
      (parseDesignDoc, validateDesignDoc, parseSpecHeader,
      validateSpecHeader) reveal the expected input/output schemas
      through their destructuring patterns and return types. This
      exposure is intentional — it makes the validation toolkit
      self-documenting for both human maintainers and LLM agents
      exploring the codebase. Any consumer reading the module can
      infer schema requirements (spec_id, spec_version, supersedes,
      delta structure, etc.) without reading sdd-schemas/ files.
      This property has testing-methodology implications documented
      in nfr-003.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-006-ac1">
        A consumer (human or LLM agent) reading scripts/lib/sdd-utils.js
        MUST be able to identify the expected fields of a spec identity
        header (spec_id, spec_version, supersedes, delta structure,
        added/modified/removed/renamed children) from the parseSpecHeader
        return destructuring alone, without consulting any external
        documentation.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-006-ac2">
        When sdd-utils.js function signatures change (adding, removing,
        or renaming returned fields), the format contracts in
        scripts/lib/sdd-schemas/ MUST be updated in the same iteration.
        The two layers describe the same underlying schema — sdd-utils
        enforces it, sdd-schemas documents it. Drift between them is ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-007">
    <title>_pending-conflict.md Handoff Schema</title>
    <description>
      The _pending-conflict.md file is the interface contract between
      refiner (producer, on R3 axis-1/2/3 block per fr-rf-015) and
      brainstorming (consumer, in Phase 0 iterate-branch auto-entry per
      fr-bs-008). This contract defines the file's location, lifecycle,
      and required content fields. Per A.1's narrowed Iron Law clause 3,
      this artifact is the explicit ephemeral exception to "no
      authoritative state on block" — non-versioned, non-authoritative,
      and consumed-and-deleted by brainstorming on successful new-design
      write.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-007-ac1">
        File location MUST be specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md.
        The underscore prefix marks the file as ephemeral hand-off, not
        versioned spec content. The file MUST NOT live under
        details/ or any path that would be parsed as a spec detail file.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-007-ac2">
        The file MUST carry: (i) which axis fired (1, 2, or 3); (ii) the
        conflict description (specific design line ranges and Q&amp;A row
        q_ids involved); (iii) 1–3 candidate resolutions, each phrased as a
        concrete action the user can pick; (iv) a user-action prompt
        directing the user to /arc-brainstorming iterate &lt;spec-id&gt;.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-007-ac3">
        Lifecycle: refiner writes the file on R3 axis-1/2/3 block per
        fr-rf-015; brainstorming reads it as Change Intent seed in Phase 0
        per fr-bs-008; brainstorming deletes it on successful new-design
        write. The file MUST NOT persist across a completed conflict
        cycle — net zero authoritative state preserved.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.2, 2026-04-27:B.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-007-ac4">
        The file MUST be machine-parseable so that brainstorming Phase 0
        can mechanically iterate over candidate resolutions and the
        cited design line ranges / Q&amp;A q_ids without LLM
        re-interpretation. The wire format (YAML, structured markdown,
        etc.) is an implementation choice; the contract is the field
        shape and machine-parseability.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-if-008">
    <title>Structured Decision-Log Format</title>
    <description>
      The decision-log is the interface contract between brainstorming
      (producer of Q&amp;A rows during Phase 2 elicitation per fr-bs-009)
      and refiner (consumer for Phase 4 axis 2 contradiction check and
      Phase 6 mechanical authorization check per fr-rf-010-ac5). This
      contract defines the field shape and machine-parseability. The wire
      format (YAML, strict markdown table, etc.) is a deliberately
      unspecified implementation choice — pinning the format here would
      over-constrain the implementation and freeze a swappable detail
      into the contract.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-008-ac1">
        Each Q&amp;A row MUST carry exactly four required fields:
        q_id (stable identifier, unique per brainstorming session),
        question (verbatim text of the question asked),
        user_answer_verbatim (verbatim text of the user's answer), and
        deferral_signal (boolean). Missing any field is ERROR.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-008-ac2">
        The decision-log MUST be machine-parseable. The producer
        (brainstorming) and consumer (refiner) MUST agree on a single wire
        format — drift between producer and consumer is ERROR. The format
        choice is an implementation decision; the spec captures the
        contract (field shape, parseability), not the format.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-008-ac3">
        Rows MUST be addressable by q_id so that refiner's Phase 6
        mechanical authorization check (per fr-rf-010-ac5) can iterate
        over rows and verify cited content appears in the correct row's
        user_answer_verbatim. Lookup by q_id MUST be a deterministic
        operation on the parsed structure.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1, 2026-04-27:B.4</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-if-008-ac4">
        The deferral_signal field MUST be set to true when the
        user_answer_verbatim matches one of the canonical deferral
        phrases ("use defaults", "covered.", "skip", "you decide", and
        similar) per fr-bs-009-ac4. deferral_signal=true tells refiner
        the corresponding axis is unbound — refiner MUST NOT treat it
        as authorization for a concrete MUST per fr-rf-013.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.1</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <!-- ═══════════════ SDD v3 Additions: Plugin Path Discipline (cc-005 enforcement) ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="fr-cc-pl-001">
    <title>Skill Path Discipline CI Lint</title>
    <description>
      cc-005 (Cross-Component Plugin Path Discipline, defined in
      spec.xml &lt;cross_cutting&gt;) requires LLM-facing prose in
      skills/, templates/, and agents/ to prefix references to plugin
      shared library content (paths under scripts/lib/) with
      ${ARCFORGE_ROOT}/. This requirement specifies the mechanical
      enforcement: a CI lint test that scans the affected files
      syntactically and fails on bare scripts/lib/ references. The
      lint scope is deliberately narrow per design.md's path-resolution
      axis — Node.js module-system paths inside scripts/lib/, test
      runner paths inside tests/, and hook paths via
      ${CLAUDE_PLUGIN_ROOT} are out-of-scope because each has a
      separate, correct mechanism. Skill-local relative patterns are
      author's judgment and not enforced.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-pl-001-ac1">
        tests/scripts/skill-path-discipline.test.js MUST exist and
        scan three globs: skills/**/SKILL.md, templates/**/*.md,
        agents/**/*.md. The scan MUST detect two violation patterns:
        (i) bare scripts/lib/ references in prose not preceded by
        ${ARCFORGE_ROOT}/ on the same logical token, and (ii)
        node -e "require('./scripts/lib/...')" cwd-relative require
        invocations. Detection MUST use regex patterns documented
        inline in the test file with rationale comments.
        <trace>design.md:Path-resolution axis section</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-pl-001-ac2">
        Each violation MUST report: file path, line number, the
        offending line content (truncated to 120 chars if longer),
        and the corrective form (${ARCFORGE_ROOT}/scripts/lib/...).
        Test failure MUST block CI and merge — there is no bypass
        annotation, no skip marker, no allowlist mechanism.
        Remediation is to fix the path; suppression is forbidden.
        <trace>design.md:Path-resolution axis section</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-pl-001-ac3">
        The lint MUST NOT scan: scripts/lib/ (Node module system
        handles cross-project safety via file-relative resolution),
        tests/ (test runner sets cwd to plugin root), hooks/ (hooks
        use ${CLAUDE_PLUGIN_ROOT} per Claude Code plugin contract),
        and skill-local paths under skills/&lt;name&gt;/scripts/ or
        skills/&lt;name&gt;/references/ that use ${SKILL_ROOT}/ or
        cd-then-bare patterns. Static analysis cannot reliably
        distinguish legitimate from broken cd-then-bare patterns
        without parsing Bash semantics; cc-005 leaves these to
        author's judgment per fr-cc-pl-001-ac1's narrowed scope.
        <trace>design.md:Path-resolution axis section</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-pl-002">
    <title>Existing P2/P3 Violation Remediation</title>
    <description>
      Landing fr-cc-pl-001 with existing violations unfixed would
      ship a broken state — the new lint would fail on the existing
      audited violations. This requirement specifies that the audited
      P2/P3 violations across the affected SDD skills MUST be fixed
      in the same v3 sprint as fr-cc-pl-001's introduction. The fix
      is mechanical (add ${ARCFORGE_ROOT}/ prefix); no semantic
      changes to SDD skill behavior are permitted under this
      requirement.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-pl-002-ac1">
        All existing bare scripts/lib/ references in skills/**/SKILL.md,
        templates/**/*.md, and agents/**/*.md MUST be prefixed with
        ${ARCFORGE_ROOT}/ such that fr-cc-pl-001-ac1's lint passes
        cleanly when v3 is merged. The audit set includes (but is not
        limited to) arc-brainstorming, arc-refining, arc-planning;
        the lint surfaces the complete current set authoritatively.
        <trace>design.md:Path-resolution axis section</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-pl-002-ac2">
        Fixes MUST be mechanical prefix additions only. Reorganizing
        Bash blocks, switching from CLI to direct read (or vice
        versa), changing skill instruction semantics, or any other
        non-prefix modification is out-of-scope for this requirement
        and MUST be tracked separately if needed.
        <trace>design.md:Path-resolution axis section</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-pl-002-ac3">
        Pre-existing arc-writing-skills Path Resolution section
        (committed at 2a189db prior to v3 sprint start) is
        considered upstream pre-work and is not subject to this
        requirement's audit — it was authored against the v3
        cc-005 contract from the outset. Any drift from the
        contract surfaced in that section MUST be fixed under
        this requirement.
        <trace>design.md:Architecture Impact section</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <!-- ═══════════════ Per-Stage Validation Pattern ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="fr-cc-val-001">
    <title>Two-Pass Write Pattern</title>
    <description>
      Stages that produce file artifacts (refiner, planner) MUST follow the
      two-pass write pattern: (1) build output in memory, (2) validate output
      against the relevant interface contract, (3) write to disk only if
      validation passes. This prevents partially written or invalid artifacts
      from reaching the filesystem.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-val-001-ac1">
        Refiner MUST NOT write spec.xml or details/ files until the complete
        output has been built in memory and validated against fr-cc-if-002.
        <trace>REQ-F012, REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-val-001-ac2">
        Planner MUST NOT write dag.yaml or epics/ until the complete output
        has been built in memory and validated for structural integrity.
        <trace>REQ-F017</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-val-001-ac3">
        When output validation fails, the stage MUST report all ERROR findings
        with remediation guidance and produce no output files.
        <trace>REQ-F008, REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cc-val-002">
    <title>Validation Report with Remediation</title>
    <description>
      When a stage blocks due to validation failure, the report MUST include
      not just what failed but how to fix it. This follows OpenSpec's enriched
      error message pattern.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-val-002-ac1">
        Each ERROR finding MUST include: the specific field or section that
        failed, the expected format (referencing the interface contract), and
        a concrete remediation suggestion.
        <trace>REQ-F009</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-val-002-ac2">
        WARNING findings MUST be reported to the user but MUST NOT block the
        stage from producing output.
        <trace>REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <!-- ═══════════════ Skill Descriptions ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="fr-cc-006">
    <title>Path-Agnostic Skill Descriptions</title>
    <description>
      Pipeline skill descriptions (frontmatter) MUST NOT hardcode artifact paths.
      Triggering conditions MUST describe intent and context, not file locations.
      The user provides the spec-id or target via their prompt.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-006-ac1">
        arc-brainstorming, arc-refining, and arc-planning descriptions MUST NOT
        contain literal paths like "specs/spec.xml" or "specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml".
        They MUST describe triggering conditions in terms of user intent (e.g.,
        "when converting design documents to structured specs").
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-006-ac2">
        Each pipeline skill MUST accept a spec-id from the user's prompt as the
        primary routing input. The skill resolves the spec-id to the correct
        artifact paths internally.
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cc-006-ac3">
        When the user does not provide a spec-id, the skill MUST scan specs/ and
        docs/plans/ to present available targets and ask the user to choose.
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <!-- ═══════════════ Non-Functional Requirements ═══════════════ -->

  <requirement id="nfr-001">
    <title>Existing Infrastructure Compatibility</title>
    <description>
      The SDD pipeline MUST work with arcforge's existing CLI and skill
      infrastructure. No new runtime dependencies.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="nfr-001-ac1">
        All pipeline operations MUST be invocable via existing arcforge skill
        mechanism (arc-brainstorming, arc-refining, arc-planning) or their
        updated versions.
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="nfr-001-ac2">
        No new npm packages MUST be added to package.json dependencies.
        devDependencies are exempt.
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="nfr-002">
    <title>File-Based Artifacts</title>
    <description>
      All artifacts MUST be file-based (YAML, XML, Markdown). No database,
      no server, no external state store.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="nfr-002-ac1">
        Pipeline state MUST be fully derivable from files on disk. Running
        `ls` and `cat` on the specs/ and docs/plans/ directories MUST be
        sufficient to determine the complete pipeline state.
        <trace>REQ-N002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="nfr-002-ac2">
        No pipeline operation MUST require network access, a running server,
        or a database connection.
        <trace>REQ-N002</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="nfr-003">
    <title>Skill Adherence Evaluation Methodology</title>
    <description>
      SDD pipeline skills (arc-brainstorming, arc-refining, arc-planning)
      cannot be reliably evaluated via A/B comparison (baseline vs
      treatment) on format-correctness output. The self-documenting
      nature of sdd-utils.js (fr-cc-if-006) means a competent baseline
      agent can infer the correct output format by reading the module,
      closing the delta between baseline and treatment. This property
      was empirically confirmed during the 2026-04-17 eval session
      against Claude Sonnet 4.x and Opus 4.x models.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="nfr-003-ac1">
        A/B evaluation of SDD pipeline skills MAY yield delta near zero
        on specific eval shapes — notably, iteration-happy-path cases
        where a valid prior spec.xml is pre-staged in the sandbox and
        the baseline agent can mimic its schema. This is a consequence
        of model capability combined with fr-cc-if-006, not a skill
        deficiency. The 2026-04-19 eval session empirically confirmed
        this zero-delta pattern on arc-refining v2-iteration-happy-path
        (with v1 fixture pre-staged) while SIMULTANEOUSLY finding large
        positive deltas on first-formalization and scope-discipline evals
        (arc-refining v1-first-formalization: +62 pts; arc-planning
        v1-plan-all-requirements: +29 pts; arc-brainstorming
        pressure-skip-exploration: +80 pts). Eval designers MUST NOT
        interpret a specific zero-delta case as "skill adds no value"
        and MUST NOT generalize it to all SDD evals.
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="nfr-003-ac2">
        The preferred eval form for SDD pipeline skills is single-condition
        agent evaluation (pass@k on treatment trials only), measuring
        reliability across k trials rather than behavioral delta against
        a non-discriminative baseline. SHIP threshold: pass rate &gt;= 80%
        across k &gt;= 5 trials after accounting for harness noise
        (grader failures, max_turns truncation).
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="nfr-003-ac3">
        Behaviors that CAN be discriminatively A/B tested for these skills
        are those NOT inferable from sdd-utils.js source alone — examples
        include: refiner DAG completion gate blocking behavior (fr-rf-012),
        terminal block message structure on contradiction (fr-rf-001-ac4),
        delta accumulation discipline (fr-rf-011-ac4), error recovery
        ordering, block-vs-proceed decisions. These remain candidates for
        focused A/B eval when discrimination is required.
        <trace>REQ-N001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
