<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="refiner">
  <title>Stage 2 — Refiner (Formalize)</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>docs/plans/&lt;spec-id&gt;/&lt;date&gt;/design.md (complete design doc)</artifact>
    <artifact>specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml (when a prior spec exists)</artifact>
    <artifact>specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml (when a prior spec exists, for completion gate check per fr-rf-012)</artifact>
    <artifact>structured decision-log per fr-cc-if-008 (when brainstorming Q&amp;A produced one; consumed for Phase 4 axis 2 check and Phase 6 mechanical authorization check per fr-rf-010)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml</artifact>
    <artifact>specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/details/*.xml</artifact>
    <artifact>specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md (ephemeral handoff on R3 axis-1/2/3 block per fr-rf-015; consumed-and-deleted by brainstorming per fr-bs-008)</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-001">
    <title>Three-Axis R3 Contradiction Check</title>
    <description>
      Refiner MUST block when any of three contradiction axes fires, per Rule R3
      (Block on Contradictions). The three axes:
      (1) design.md internal contradictions — including conflict between new
      design requirements and existing spec requirements when a prior spec
      exists, and broken dependencies on removed requirements;
      (2) design.md ↔ user Q&amp;A — design says X and a structured decision-log
      row says ¬X; refiner has no authorization to silently pick either side;
      (3) spec-draft coverage — every produced criterion must trace to a
      (design phrase ∪ Q&amp;A row) source; criteria with no such source are
      invention.
      Phasing: axes 1 and 2 are checked at Phase 4 (pre-draft, LLM judgment);
      axis 3 has LLM judgment at Phase 5.5 (per fr-rf-014) and mechanical
      enforcement at Phase 6 (per fr-rf-010). On any axis firing, refiner blocks:
      no spec.xml, no details/, no narrative report — the only persistent
      artifact written is the ephemeral handoff at
      specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md (per fr-rf-015), which is
      non-versioned and consumed-and-deleted by brainstorming per fr-bs-008.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-001-ac1">
        Given a design doc where REQ-A requires "sessions expire after 15 minutes"
        and REQ-B requires "sessions never expire", refiner MUST block on axis 1
        with the contradiction printed to terminal including specific requirement
        IDs and a pointer to specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md. Refiner
        MUST exit non-zero.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.2</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-001-ac2">
        Given a design phrase saying X and a structured decision-log row saying
        ¬X, refiner MUST block on axis 2. Silently picking either side is
        forbidden — even if the Q&amp;A answer is more recent than the design.
        Terminal output MUST cite both the design line range and the Q&amp;A
        q_id; the _pending-conflict.md handoff carries at least one candidate
        resolution per side ("keep design wording", "accept Q&amp;A answer",
        "make the axis configurable so both stances coexist").
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.2</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-001-ac3">
        When blocked on any axis (1, 2, or 3), refiner MUST NOT write any
        authoritative artifact — no spec.xml, no file under
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/details/, no refiner-report.md or any other
        persistent narrative reporting artifact. The only persistent artifact
        permitted on R3 axis-1/2/3 block is the ephemeral handoff
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md per fr-rf-015, which is
        non-versioned and consumed-and-deleted by brainstorming on successful
        new-design write per fr-bs-008.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-001-ac4">
        Terminal output on block MUST list each detected issue with: (i) which
        axis fired (1, 2, or 3) and a one-line description; (ii) the specific
        design line ranges and Q&amp;A row q_ids involved. The 1–3 candidate
        resolutions and the user-action prompt directing the user to
        /arc-brainstorming iterate &lt;spec-id&gt; are written to
        _pending-conflict.md per fr-rf-015 — terminal output points the user
        to that file.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.2, 2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-003">
    <title>Spec Identity Header</title>
    <description>
      Every spec.xml MUST contain an identity header with spec_id, spec_version,
      status, source (design path + iteration date), scope, and supersedes fields.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-003-ac1">
        A newly created spec.xml MUST have spec_version: 1, status: active, and
        supersedes empty or absent.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-003-ac2">
        An updated spec.xml MUST have spec_version: base_version + 1, and
        supersedes set to "&lt;spec-id&gt;:v&lt;previous-version&gt;".
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-003-ac3">
        The source element MUST contain design_path pointing to the exact design
        doc file and design_iteration matching the design doc folder name.
        The folder name MUST start with an ISO date (YYYY-MM-DD) and MAY include
        a "-"-separated human-chosen suffix (e.g., "2026-04-16-v2" for same-date
        sequential iterations, "2026-04-16-oauth-pivot" for intent-tagged
        iterations). The suffix is a human convention, not a schema constraint.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-003-ac4">
        The scope element MUST list included features with IDs and excluded items
        with reasons.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-004">
    <title>Per-Spec Directory Isolation</title>
    <description>
      Multiple specs MUST coexist in separate specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/ folders. Each
      folder is a self-contained project unit.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-004-ac1">
        Given spec-ids "auth" and "payments", their specs MUST reside at
        specs/auth/spec.xml and specs/payments/spec.xml respectively, with no
        cross-folder references.
        <trace>REQ-F011</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-004-ac2">
        Each spec folder MUST contain its own details/ subdirectory. Detail files
        MUST NOT reference requirements from other spec folders.
        <trace>REQ-F011</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-005">
    <title>Formalize Spec From Design Doc</title>
    <description>
      Refiner MUST read the complete design doc and produce or update a spec.
      There is no explicit mode distinction — the refiner checks whether
      specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml exists and adapts accordingly. When no
      existing spec is found, it formalizes from scratch. When an existing
      spec is found, it reads the design doc (Change Intent) alongside the
      existing spec, determines what changed, and updates the spec — like
      wiki ingest propagation.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-005-ac1">
        When no existing spec.xml is found, refiner MUST produce a spec.xml
        with spec_version: 1 and detail files covering all requirements
        identified in the design doc, each with at least one acceptance
        criterion and trace.
        <trace>REQ-F012</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-005-ac2">
        When an existing spec.xml is found, refiner MUST read both the
        design doc and the existing spec. ADDED items result in new
        requirements; MODIFIED items update existing requirements in place;
        REMOVED items delete requirements from detail files.
        <trace>REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-005-ac3">
        When updating an existing spec, requirements NOT affected by the
        design doc's change intent MUST remain unchanged in the output spec.
        <trace>REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-005-ac4">
        A complete rewrite (aggressive iteration where the Change Intent
        replaces everything) MUST be handled by the same behavior — the
        refiner does not switch to a "replace" code path. The design doc's
        Change Intent drives what gets added/modified/removed/renamed; the
        refiner emits a correspondingly large &lt;delta&gt;. No mode labels,
        no separate behavior — just one refiner that produces whatever
        delta the situation requires.
        <trace>REQ-F012, REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-011">
    <title>Delta Metadata Output — Wiki-Style Accumulation</title>
    <description>
      When updating an existing spec, refiner MUST append a new &lt;delta&gt;
      element to the spec's &lt;overview&gt; recording what changed in this
      version. Refiner MUST NOT overwrite, modify, or remove prior &lt;delta&gt;
      elements — they are historical record. &lt;overview&gt; accumulates all
      &lt;delta&gt; children ordered ascending by version, producing a
      self-contained iteration history inside the spec (wiki-style, per
      Karpathy three-layer model). This metadata stays within the spec (wiki
      layer) so the planner can determine planning scope without reading the
      design doc (raw source layer).
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-011-ac1">
        A new &lt;delta&gt; element MUST include: version (matching the new
        spec_version), iteration (matching the new design_iteration), and
        child elements for each change. Supported child elements are
        &lt;added ref="req-id" /&gt;, &lt;modified ref="req-id" /&gt;,
        &lt;removed ref="req-id"&gt;&lt;reason&gt;...&lt;/reason&gt;&lt;/removed&gt;
        (reason required; optional &lt;migration&gt; child), and
        &lt;renamed ref_old="..." ref_new="..."&gt; (optional &lt;reason&gt;;
        body unchanged — semantic changes use removed+added, not renamed).
        <trace>REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-011-ac2">
        For a new spec (no prior version), no delta element is written.
        Absence of any &lt;delta&gt; in &lt;overview&gt; signals "plan all
        requirements" to the planner.
        <trace>REQ-F012</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-011-ac3">
        Every requirement ID referenced in the new delta MUST correspond to
        an actual requirement in the spec's detail files (for added/modified/
        renamed.ref_new) or to a requirement that existed in a prior version
        (for removed.ref and renamed.ref_old).
        <trace>REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-011-ac4">
        Refiner MUST preserve all prior &lt;delta&gt; elements verbatim when
        writing the new spec. The new &lt;delta&gt; is appended as the last
        child of &lt;overview&gt;. The resulting sequence MUST be ordered
        ascending by version. Refiner MUST NOT merge, deduplicate, or rewrite
        historical deltas.
        <trace>REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-011-ac5">
        The new delta's version attribute MUST equal the new spec_version.
        The new delta's iteration attribute MUST equal the new design_iteration.
        Mismatch is ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-012">
    <title>DAG Completion Gate (Upstream of New Iteration)</title>
    <description>
      Before producing a new spec version (one that would append a &lt;delta&gt;
      and increment spec_version), refiner MUST check the current
      specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml for sprint completion. This gate lives in
      refiner, not planner, so that inconsistent wiki-layer state ("spec at
      v(N+1) while prior sprint's DAG is still incomplete") never arises. If
      the gate blocks, nothing downstream moves — spec stays at v(N), DAG
      stays at v(N)'s execution state, user completes the work or abandons
      the entire spec, then the refiner may run cleanly.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-012-ac1">
        When no prior spec.xml exists, refiner MUST NOT perform the gate check
        (there is no prior sprint to be incomplete). Refiner proceeds as v1
        formalization.
        <trace>REQ-F023</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-012-ac2">
        When a prior spec.xml exists AND no dag.yaml exists at
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/dag.yaml, refiner MUST proceed. This is a legal
        state (user refined without planning yet).
        <trace>REQ-F023</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-012-ac3">
        When a prior spec.xml exists AND dag.yaml exists AND all epics in
        dag.yaml are in "completed" status, refiner MUST proceed with the
        new iteration.
        <trace>REQ-F023</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-012-ac4">
        When a prior spec.xml exists AND dag.yaml exists AND any epic is NOT
        in "completed" status, refiner MUST BLOCK. It MUST print to terminal:
        the number of incomplete epics, the specific epic IDs and their
        statuses, and the message "Complete current sprint before iterating."
        Refiner MUST exit non-zero. No spec file is written, no &lt;delta&gt;
        is added, nothing changes on disk. No refiner-report.md is written.
        <trace>REQ-F023</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-012-ac5">
        Refiner MUST NOT implement any escape hatch for the gate — no
        --force flag, no environment variable override, no "abandoned" epic
        status that bypasses the check. The only legitimate paths forward
        when blocked are: (a) the user completes the remaining epics, or
        (b) the user abandons the entire spec by deleting
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/ (which is a filesystem action outside
        refiner's scope). Partial abandonment is rejected by design because
        it would pollute dag.yaml status semantics.
        <trace>REQ-F023</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-007">
    <title>Spec Version Increment</title>
    <description>
      When updating an existing spec, refiner MUST increment the spec version
      and record supersedes. The planner uses spec_version to locate the
      correct delta for planning scope.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-007-ac1">
        Updated spec.xml MUST have spec_version = previous version + 1.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-007-ac2">
        Updated spec.xml MUST set supersedes to
        "&lt;spec-id&gt;:v&lt;previous-version&gt;".
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-007-ac3">
        Updated spec.xml source MUST point to the new design doc iteration
        that triggered this update.
        <trace>REQ-F010</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-008">
    <title>Merged Spec Validation</title>
    <description>
      After producing a new or updated spec, refiner MUST validate that the
      resulting spec has no internal contradictions before writing output.
      This requirement covers inter-requirement merge contradictions —
      contradictions across requirements introduced by merging the design's
      Change Intent with the prior spec. Intra-requirement self-contradictions
      (description ↔ AC scope mismatches, RFC-2119 verb mismatches inside a
      single requirement) are covered separately by fr-rf-014's Phase 5.5
      sub-pass.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-008-ac1">
        Given an update that adds a requirement contradicting an existing
        requirement, refiner MUST block per fr-rf-001 (terminal output,
        non-zero exit, no files written). The contradiction MUST be
        described in terminal output with specific requirement IDs.
        <trace>REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-008-ac2">
        Given an update that modifies a requirement into contradiction with
        another requirement, refiner MUST block.
        <trace>REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-008-ac3">
        Given an update that removes a requirement depended on by another
        requirement still in the spec, refiner MUST block with a "dependency
        broken" issue.
        <trace>REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-009">
    <title>Input Validation — Design Doc</title>
    <description>
      Before any formalization, refiner MUST validate its input per the
      design doc contract (fr-cc-if-001). All validation checks run before
      any output is produced. The refiner consumes the complete design doc.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-009-ac1">
        Refiner MUST verify the design doc file exists at the provided path.
        Missing file is ERROR with remediation: "Run brainstorming to produce
        a design doc first."
        <trace>REQ-F008</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-009-ac2">
        Refiner MUST check filesystem state to decide whether version-dependent
        fields are produced: if specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/spec.xml exists → read
        existing spec + design doc, produce updated spec with incremented
        spec_version, supersedes, and a new &lt;delta&gt;. If not → read design
        doc, produce new spec with spec_version=1, no supersedes, no delta.
        This is a single behavior with conditional fields, not two modes.
        <trace>REQ-F012, REQ-F013</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-009-ac3">
        When a prior spec exists, refiner MUST validate that the design doc
        has the required sections for an iteration design doc: Context
        section (with spec version reference) and Change Intent section
        present. Missing required sections is ERROR with remediation: "When a
        prior spec exists, the design doc must include Context and Change
        Intent sections — re-run brainstorming with the prior spec in scope."
        <trace>REQ-F005, REQ-F008</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-009-ac4">
        When a prior spec exists, if the design doc's date folder is older
        than or equal to the spec's recorded design_iteration, refiner MUST
        produce WARNING: "design iteration &lt;date&gt; is not newer than
        spec source &lt;spec-date&gt; — this may be a stale design doc."
        <trace>REQ-F026</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-010">
    <title>Output Validation — Two-Pass Write with Mechanical Authorization Check</title>
    <description>
      Refiner MUST follow the two-pass write pattern (fr-cc-val-001): build
      the complete spec.xml and details/ in memory, validate against the Spec
      Identity Header contract (fr-cc-if-002) AND perform the mechanical
      authorization check (axis 3 enforcement at validator level), then write
      to disk only if all validation passes. The mechanical authorization
      check iterates over every &lt;trace&gt; element in the in-memory spec
      and verifies the cited content appears at the cited source location:
      for traces citing design line ranges, the cited content MUST appear at
      those lines; for traces citing Q&amp;A rows by q_id, the cited content
      MUST appear in that row's user_answer_verbatim of the structured
      decision-log. This is the validator-level layer of axis 3 enforcement;
      the LLM-judgment layer fires earlier at Phase 5.5 per fr-rf-014.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-010-ac1">
        After building spec.xml in memory, refiner MUST validate the identity
        header per fr-cc-if-002: spec_id, spec_version, status, source,
        scope all present and well-formed. Missing fields are ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F010, REQ-F015</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-010-ac2">
        Every &lt;requirement&gt; in the built output MUST have at least one
        &lt;acceptance_criteria&gt; with a &lt;trace&gt; element. Requirements without
        testable AC are ERROR.
        <trace>REQ-F012</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-010-ac3">
        If output validation finds ERRORs, refiner MUST report all findings
        with remediation guidance and MUST NOT write any authoritative files
        to specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/ (no spec.xml, no details/). The ephemeral
        _pending-conflict.md handoff per fr-rf-015 is the carved-out
        exception on R3 axis-1/2/3 blocks per ac5; for non-R3-axis ERRORs
        (e.g. identity-header errors per ac1/ac2, or schema-validation
        errors per fr-rf-010-ac1/ac2/ac4) no files MUST be written at all.
        <trace>REQ-F008, REQ-F015, 2026-04-27:A.1</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-010-ac4">
        If output validation passes (zero ERRORs), refiner MUST write all
        files atomically — spec.xml and all details/*.xml in a single
        operation. Partial writes (spec.xml written but details/ incomplete)
        MUST NOT occur.
        <trace>REQ-F012</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-010-ac5">
        Refiner MUST perform the mechanical authorization check at Phase 6.
        For every &lt;trace&gt; element in the in-memory draft: (i) if the
        trace cites a design line range, refiner MUST verify the cited
        content appears at those lines in the design doc; (ii) if the trace
        cites a Q&amp;A row by q_id, refiner MUST verify the cited content
        appears in that row's user_answer_verbatim of the structured
        decision-log per fr-cc-if-008. Any mismatch is ERROR. On axis-3
        mechanical-check ERROR, refiner MUST block per fr-rf-001 axis 3 —
        the _pending-conflict.md handoff per fr-rf-015 is written, no
        spec.xml or details/ are written.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.4</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-013">
    <title>Phase 5 No-Invention Discipline</title>
    <description>
      During Phase 5 (drafting the spec in memory), refiner MUST NOT author
      any criterion from training-data inference. When a design phrase is
      qualitative ("rate-limited", "fast", "secure") or a Q&amp;A row defers
      ("use defaults", "covered.", "skip", "you decide", or similar deferral
      phrases with deferral_signal=true per fr-cc-if-008), the legitimate
      refiner moves are exactly three:
      (a) preserve the design's qualitative phrasing as SHOULD/MAY (the
      source phrase is in design.md — that is the authorization);
      (b) leave the axis unbound (no criterion at all on that axis;
      downstream stages may surface it as a planning question);
      (c) BLOCK on axis 3 with a candidate-resolution handoff via fr-rf-015.
      Inventing a concrete MUST from training-data common practice is not
      among the legitimate moves.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-013-ac1">
        Given a design phrase "the system is rate-limited" with no concrete
        rate value, and no decision-log row resolving the rate, refiner MUST
        NOT author "rate limit MUST be 60 requests per minute" (or any other
        concrete value) — that would be invention. Legitimate moves:
        (a) emit "the system SHOULD be rate-limited" with trace to the
        qualitative design phrase; (b) leave the rate axis unbound (no
        criterion); (c) BLOCK on axis 3.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-013-ac2">
        Given a Q&amp;A row whose user_answer_verbatim matches a deferral
        signal (deferral_signal=true), refiner MUST treat the corresponding
        axis as unbound — deferral does NOT authorize a concrete MUST
        derived from training-data common practice. The three legitimate
        moves still apply.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.3</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-013-ac3">
        For every concrete MUST in the produced spec, refiner MUST be able
        to point to a non-deferral source — either a design phrase containing
        the concrete value, or a Q&amp;A row whose user_answer_verbatim
        contains the concrete value with deferral_signal=false. If no such
        source exists, the criterion is invention and MUST NOT be authored
        (use one of the three legitimate moves instead).
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.3</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-014">
    <title>Phase 5.5 — Self-Contradiction Sub-Pass and Axis 3 LLM Judgment</title>
    <description>
      Before Phase 6 output validation, refiner MUST perform a Phase 5.5 LLM
      sub-pass that hosts two checks:
      (a) self-contradiction — re-read each requirement's &lt;description&gt;
      against each &lt;criterion&gt; (and against sibling criteria) to detect
      scope mismatches (description says "the system handles X" but ACs only
      test the success path) and RFC-2119 verb mismatches (description uses
      MUST but a sibling AC uses SHOULD on the same axis);
      (b) axis 3 LLM judgment — for each criterion in the in-memory draft,
      verify a (design phrase ∪ Q&amp;A row) source can be cited; criteria
      with no citable source are invention per fr-rf-013.
      Both findings are R3 enforcement failures (BLOCK + non-zero exit + no
      spec.xml + no details/), with severity equal to Patterns 1a/1b/2 — not
      WARN. Phase 5.5 findings are not silently corrected; they BLOCK and
      route to recovery. Axis-3 LLM-coverage findings trigger the
      _pending-conflict.md handoff per fr-rf-015-ac1 (axis 3 enumerated).
      Self-contradiction findings (description ↔ AC scope mismatch and
      RFC-2119 verb mismatch per ac1/ac2) ALSO trigger the handoff so the
      user has a single one-message recovery path covering every R3 BLOCK
      surface; see ac5 for the contract.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-014-ac1">
        Given a requirement whose description says "the system handles X
        under both success and failure paths" but whose ACs only test the
        success path, refiner MUST detect the scope mismatch at Phase 5.5
        and BLOCK with terminal output including the requirement ID and a
        remediation hint ("widen ACs to cover failure path, or narrow
        description to match ACs").
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.4</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-014-ac2">
        Given a requirement whose description uses "MUST validate" but
        whose AC for the same axis uses "SHOULD validate" (or vice versa),
        refiner MUST detect the RFC-2119 verb mismatch at Phase 5.5 and
        BLOCK with terminal output including the requirement ID and a
        remediation hint ("align verbs across description and ACs for the
        same axis").
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.4</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-014-ac3">
        Phase 5.5 MUST also perform axis 3 coverage LLM judgment: for every
        criterion in the in-memory draft, refiner verifies a citable source
        (design phrase or non-deferral Q&amp;A row) exists. Criteria with no
        citable source trigger BLOCK per fr-rf-001 axis 3. This is the
        LLM-judgment layer; the mechanical layer fires at Phase 6 per
        fr-rf-010-ac5.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.2, 2026-04-27:A.4</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-014-ac4">
        On any Phase 5.5 finding (self-contradiction per ac1/ac2 OR axis-3
        LLM coverage per ac3), refiner MUST treat it as R3 enforcement
        severity — exit non-zero, no spec.xml, no details/, no narrative
        report. Phase 5.5 findings MUST NOT be downgraded to WARNING. A
        WARN would let the spec ship with internal contradictions, which is
        precisely Pattern 3 of the eval evidence.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.4</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-014-ac5">
        On any Phase 5.5 finding (self-contradiction per ac1/ac2 OR axis-3
        LLM coverage per ac3), refiner MUST also write the
        _pending-conflict.md handoff per fr-rf-015's contract. This is the
        single recovery surface for every R3 BLOCK — self-contradiction is
        not exempted. The seed conflict_description carries the
        requirement ID and the relevant remediation hint from ac1/ac2/ac3.
        <trace>2026-04-27:A.4, 2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-rf-015">
    <title>_pending-conflict.md Write-on-Block Contract</title>
    <description>
      When refiner blocks on axis 1, 2, or 3 (per fr-rf-001), it MUST write
      a single structured handoff file at
      specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md and exit non-zero. Per
      A.1's narrowed Iron Law clause 3 (NEVER WRITE AUTHORITATIVE STATE ON
      BLOCK), this file is the explicit ephemeral exception: non-versioned,
      non-authoritative, and consumed-and-deleted by brainstorming on
      successful new-design write per fr-bs-008. The file's purpose is to
      enable arc-brainstorming Phase 0 iterate-branch auto-entry without
      requiring the user to retell the conflict.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-015-ac1">
        On axis-1, axis-2, or axis-3 block (per fr-rf-001 or per fr-rf-010-ac5
        for axis-3 mechanical), refiner MUST write
        specs/&lt;spec-id&gt;/_pending-conflict.md with content per
        fr-cc-if-007: which axis fired (1, 2, or 3), the conflict description
        (specific design line ranges and Q&amp;A row q_ids involved), 1–3
        candidate resolutions, and a user-action prompt directing the user
        to /arc-brainstorming iterate &lt;spec-id&gt;.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-rf-015-ac2">
        Refiner MUST NOT write _pending-conflict.md for non-R3-axis blocks:
        DAG completion gate failure per fr-rf-012, design-doc validation
        failure per fr-rf-009, or identity-header validation errors per
        fr-rf-010-ac1 through fr-rf-010-ac4. These are pipeline-mechanical
        or programmer-error blocks, not axis contradictions; their output
        channels are terminal and exit code only.
        <trace>2026-04-27:B.2</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
