<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<spec>
  <overview>
    <spec_id>spec-driven-refine</spec_id>
    <spec_version>2</spec_version>
    <status>active</status>
    <supersedes>spec-driven-refine:v1</supersedes>
    <source>
      <design_path>docs/plans/spec-driven-refine/2026-04-16-v2/design.md</design_path>
      <design_iteration>2026-04-16-v2</design_iteration>
    </source>
    <title>Spec-Driven Development Pipeline</title>
    <description>
      Convert arcforge's one-shot brainstorming-refiner-planner pipeline into an
      iterable Spec-Driven Development workflow. Design docs become immutable raw
      sources; specs become live contracts updated via delta integration; DAGs become
      derived views that preserve execution state. Three foundational rules (R1 Human
      Consent, R2 Unidirectional Flow, R3 Block on Contradictions) govern the entire flow.
    </description>
    <scope>
      <includes>
        <feature id="stage-1-brainstorming">Scan existing specs, confirm spec target, produce design doc with context-sensitive sections (prose when no prior spec; Context + Change Intent when prior spec exists), output validation</feature>
        <feature id="stage-2-refiner">One behavior with conditional fields based on filesystem state, wiki-style accumulating delta output, DAG completion gate upstream of iteration, R3 block via terminal (no persistent artifact), input/output validation</feature>
        <feature id="stage-3-planner">Pure function (spec + delta) → (dag.yaml + epics/), overwrite DAG each sprint (no archive, no state preservation, no gate), delta-scoped planning with epic generation for added/modified/removed/renamed, 1:1 mapping, done signal, input/output validation</feature>
        <feature id="cross-cutting-rules">R1 (human consent), R2 (unidirectional), R3 (block on contradictions)</feature>
        <feature id="artifact-layout">Directory structure for designs, specs, DAG (per-spec)</feature>
        <feature id="spec-identity-header">XML schema for spec self-identification, versioning, and wiki-style accumulating delta metadata</feature>
        <feature id="interface-contracts">Design Doc and Spec Identity Header format contracts — sdd-schemas/ (guidance) + sdd-utils.js (validation toolkit)</feature>
        <feature id="per-stage-validation">Input/output validation at each pipeline stage with three-tier severity, two-pass write, and deterministic/semantic split</feature>
      </includes>
      <excludes>
        <reason>Cross-spec dependencies — deferred until multi-spec usage is established</reason>
        <reason>Downstream migration (Phase 2) — coordinator.js per-spec DAG support, CLI --spec parameter, loop.js multi-spec parallelism, skill path updates, worktree marker spec_id</reason>
      </excludes>
    </scope>

    <delta version="2" iteration="2026-04-16-v2">
      <modified ref="fr-bs-003">Remove REFINER_INPUT from the output format used when no prior spec exists</modified>
      <modified ref="fr-bs-005">Remove structured Delta from the output format used when prior spec exists; use natural-language Change Intent only</modified>
      <removed ref="fr-bs-007">
        <reason>Change Type Derivation — replaced by output validation (fr-bs-007 repurposed)</reason>
      </removed>
      <modified ref="fr-rf-005">Consolidate the single refiner behavior, removing "initial vs iteration" mode language</modified>
      <removed ref="fr-rf-006">
        <reason>Separate iteration mode — merged into fr-rf-005 (one behavior, not two modes)</reason>
      </removed>
      <added ref="fr-rf-011">Delta metadata output — refiner writes delta element to spec overview (accumulates wiki-style per 2026-04-19 realignment, see [[arcforge-decision-sdd-v2-pipeline-realignment]])</added>
      <added ref="fr-rf-012">DAG completion gate — refiner blocks new iteration if prior sprint has incomplete epics (introduced in 2026-04-19 realignment; gate moved here from planner.fr-pl-007 which was removed)</added>
      <modified ref="fr-pl-001">Planner as pure function — overwrite DAG each sprint, scope by delta matching current spec_version, all four delta children generate epics, no archive, no state preservation, no gate (gate moved to refiner)</modified>
      <removed ref="fr-cc-003">
        <reason>Stale lint design-newer-than-spec — replaced by per-stage validation</reason>
      </removed>
      <removed ref="fr-cc-004">
        <reason>Stale lint unrefined-design — replaced by per-stage validation</reason>
      </removed>
      <removed ref="fr-cc-005">
        <reason>Stale lint unplanned-spec — replaced by per-stage validation</reason>
      </removed>
      <modified ref="fr-cc-if-004">Clarify sdd-utils.js as validation toolkit, not merge engine</modified>
      <modified ref="fr-cc-if-005">Add three-layer rationale for planner not reading design doc</modified>
    </delta>
  </overview>

  <cross_cutting>
    <constraint id="cc-001">
      <title>Zero External Dependencies</title>
      <description>Node.js standard library only. No npm runtime dependencies.</description>
    </constraint>
    <constraint id="cc-003">
      <title>Three-Tier Validation Severity</title>
      <description>
        All per-stage validation uses three severity levels: ERROR (blocks stage,
        no output produced), WARNING (continues but alerts user), INFO (informational).
        A stage is "valid" when it has zero ERRORs.
      </description>
    </constraint>
    <constraint id="cc-004">
      <title>Self-Contained Stage Input</title>
      <description>
        Each pipeline stage receives a self-contained input: the complete design
        doc for refiner, the complete spec.xml for planner. Stages MUST NOT rely
        on implicit context from prior conversation or session state.
      </description>
    </constraint>
  </cross_cutting>

  <details>
    <detail_file path="details/brainstorming.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/refiner.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/planner.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/cross-cutting.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/sdd-schemas.xml" />
  </details>
</spec>
