<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<spec>
  <overview>
    <spec_id>spec-driven-refine</spec_id>
    <spec_version>2</spec_version>
    <supersedes>spec-driven-refine:v1</supersedes>
    <status>active</status>
    <source>
      <design_path>docs/plans/spec-driven-refine/2026-04-27/design.md</design_path>
      <design_iteration>2026-04-27</design_iteration>
    </source>
    <title>Spec-Driven Development Pipeline</title>
    <description>
      Convert arcforge's one-shot brainstorming-refiner-planner pipeline into an
      iterable Spec-Driven Development workflow. Design docs become immutable raw
      sources; specs become live contracts updated via delta integration; DAGs become
      derived views that preserve execution state. Three foundational rules (R1 Human
      Consent, R2 Unidirectional Flow, R3 Block on Contradictions) govern the entire flow.
    </description>
    <scope>
      <includes>
        <feature id="stage-1-brainstorming">Scan existing specs, confirm spec target, produce design doc with context-sensitive sections (prose when no prior spec; Context + Change Intent when prior spec exists), Phase 0 pending-conflict detection with iterate-branch auto-entry, structured decision-log Q&amp;A output, output validation</feature>
        <feature id="stage-2-refiner">One behavior with conditional fields based on filesystem state, wiki-style accumulating delta output, DAG completion gate upstream of iteration, three-axis R3 contradiction check (design internal, design ↔ Q&amp;A, criterion coverage), Phase 5 no-invention discipline, Phase 5.5 self-contradiction sub-pass, R3 block via terminal (no authoritative artifact; ephemeral _pending-conflict.md handoff to brainstorming on axis-1/2/3 block), input/output validation including Phase 6 mechanical authorization check over &lt;trace&gt; elements</feature>
        <feature id="stage-3-planner">Pure function (spec + delta) → (dag.yaml + epics/), overwrite DAG each sprint (no archive, no state preservation, no gate), delta-scoped planning with epic generation for added/modified/removed/renamed, 1:1 mapping, done signal, input/output validation</feature>
        <feature id="cross-cutting-rules">R1 (human consent), R2 (unidirectional), R3 (block on contradictions)</feature>
        <feature id="artifact-layout">Directory structure for designs, specs, DAG (per-spec), and the ephemeral _pending-conflict.md handoff</feature>
        <feature id="spec-identity-header">XML schema for spec self-identification, versioning, and wiki-style accumulating delta metadata</feature>
        <feature id="interface-contracts">Design Doc, Spec Identity Header, _pending-conflict.md handoff, and structured decision-log format contracts — sdd-schemas/ (guidance) + sdd-utils.js (validation toolkit)</feature>
        <feature id="per-stage-validation">Input/output validation at each pipeline stage with three-tier severity, two-pass write, deterministic/semantic split, and Phase 6 mechanical authorization check (axis 3 enforcement at validator level)</feature>
      </includes>
      <excludes>
        <reason>Cross-spec dependencies — deferred until multi-spec usage is established</reason>
        <reason>Downstream migration (Phase 2) — coordinator.js per-spec DAG support, CLI --spec parameter, loop.js multi-spec parallelism, skill path updates, worktree marker spec_id</reason>
        <reason>Stage 3 cross-model audit pass — proposal's optional defense-in-depth (different-model judge re-reads in-memory spec inside Phase 5.5); deferred unless same-model-bias check shows &gt;1 finding divergence</reason>
        <reason>Cleanup of deprecated fr-cc-if-003 (SDD Schemas Guidance Layer) — the v1 requirement that scripts/lib/sdd-schemas/design.md and spec.md exist remains valid as artifact-location spec; per fr-sd-011-ac3 those files are deprecated as SoT but remain as artifacts. Removing fr-cc-if-003 would also require removing those files; that scope-creep does not belong in this R3-enforcement iteration.</reason>
      </excludes>
    </scope>
    <delta version="2" iteration="2026-04-27">
      <modified ref="fr-rf-001" />
      <modified ref="fr-rf-010" />
      <added ref="fr-rf-013" />
      <added ref="fr-rf-014" />
      <added ref="fr-rf-015" />
      <added ref="fr-bs-008" />
      <added ref="fr-bs-009" />
      <added ref="fr-cc-if-007" />
      <added ref="fr-cc-if-008" />
      <added ref="fr-sd-012" />
      <added ref="fr-sd-013" />
      <added ref="fr-sd-014" />
    </delta>
  </overview>

  <cross_cutting>
    <constraint id="cc-001">
      <title>Zero External Dependencies</title>
      <description>Node.js standard library only. No npm runtime dependencies.</description>
    </constraint>
    <constraint id="cc-003">
      <title>Three-Tier Validation Severity</title>
      <description>
        All per-stage validation uses three severity levels: ERROR (blocks stage,
        no output produced), WARNING (continues but alerts user), INFO (informational).
        A stage is "valid" when it has zero ERRORs.
      </description>
    </constraint>
    <constraint id="cc-004">
      <title>Self-Contained Stage Input</title>
      <description>
        Each pipeline stage receives a self-contained input: the complete design
        doc for refiner, the complete spec.xml for planner. Stages MUST NOT rely
        on implicit context from prior conversation or session state.
      </description>
    </constraint>
  </cross_cutting>

  <details>
    <detail_file path="details/brainstorming.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/refiner.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/planner.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/cross-cutting.xml" />
    <detail_file path="details/sdd-schemas.xml" />
  </details>
</spec>
