<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="cli-subcommands">
  <title>New CLI Subcommands — preflight / lint / audit</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>evals/scenarios/*.md (scenario definitions)</artifact>
    <artifact>evals/benchmarks/latest.json (historical benchmark data)</artifact>
    <artifact>scripts/lib/eval.js (harness entry points)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>evals/preflight/&lt;scenario-hash&gt;.json (preflight pass/block records)</artifact>
    <artifact>arc eval lint terminal output (validation errors + warnings)</artifact>
    <artifact>arc eval audit terminal output (assertion promotion and retirement candidate lists)</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-cli-001">
    <title>arc eval preflight Subcommand</title>
    <description>
      A new arc eval preflight &lt;scenario&gt; subcommand MUST run 2–3 baseline pilot
      trials against the scenario (no skill, no treatment), compute pass rate, and
      record the result keyed by scenario hash. Outcomes: PASS when baseline pass
      rate is below the ceiling threshold (0.8 by default); BLOCK when the ceiling
      is reached, signaling the scenario is not discriminative. Subsequent arc
      eval ab runs against the same scenario hash MUST require a prior PASS
      preflight record; missing or stale records MUST block ab with a clear
      remediation message. Scenario hash is computed deterministically from the
      scenario file contents, so unchanged scenarios skip preflight transparently.
      Preflight is exempt from the k≥5 verdict policy (fr-vr-001) because it
      checks scenario validity, not shipping fitness — its output is PASS/BLOCK,
      never SHIP/INSUFFICIENT_DATA.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-001-ac1">
        Given a scenario that has never been preflighted, arc eval ab MUST refuse
        to run and MUST print a message instructing the user to run
        arc eval preflight first.
        <trace>fr-cli-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-001-ac2">
        Given a scenario whose baseline pass rate across 2–3 pilot trials is ≥ 0.8,
        arc eval preflight MUST output BLOCK with a clear explanation (baseline
        ceiling reached) and MUST persist the block record keyed by scenario hash.
        <trace>fr-cli-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-001-ac3">
        Given a previously preflighted scenario whose file contents are unchanged
        (identical hash), arc eval ab MUST run without re-requiring preflight.
        <trace>fr-cli-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-001-ac4">
        Given a scenario edited after a prior preflight, the scenario hash MUST
        differ and arc eval ab MUST refuse until preflight is re-run.
        <trace>fr-cli-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-001-ac5">
        arc eval preflight MUST NOT emit SHIP, NEEDS_WORK, BLOCKED, or
        INSUFFICIENT_DATA verdicts. Its only outputs are PASS and BLOCK.
        <trace>fr-cli-001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cli-002">
    <title>arc eval lint Subcommand</title>
    <description>
      A new arc eval lint &lt;scenario&gt; subcommand MUST validate a scenario file
      against a JSON Schema covering required sections (Context, Setup, Grader
      Config, Assertions), section format, assertion shape, and grader config
      shape. Errors MUST be reported with file location and remediation. Lint
      MUST exit non-zero on any schema violation.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-002-ac1">
        Given a scenario with a well-formed structure, arc eval lint MUST exit 0
        and print "ok".
        <trace>fr-cli-002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-002-ac2">
        Given a scenario missing a required section such as "## Assertions", arc
        eval lint MUST exit non-zero and print a diagnostic identifying the
        missing section and the expected location.
        <trace>fr-cli-002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-002-ac3">
        Given a scenario with an assertion entry that lacks a grader-type field,
        arc eval lint MUST exit non-zero and report the specific assertion id.
        <trace>fr-cli-002</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-cli-003">
    <title>arc eval audit Subcommand</title>
    <description>
      A new arc eval audit subcommand MUST aggregate discovered_claims[] and
      weak_assertions[] across the entire benchmark history and emit two lists:
      "promotion candidates" (claims that recur frequently and fail often —
      candidates for elevation to formal assertions) and "retirement candidates"
      (assertions repeatedly flagged as weak or non-discriminative). Output MUST
      include frequency counts, originating scenarios, and a stable hash so the
      same audit run is reproducible.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-003-ac1">
        Given a benchmark history containing at least 10 graded trials across
        multiple scenarios, arc eval audit MUST emit at least one promotion
        candidate or one retirement candidate, each with frequency data.
        <trace>fr-cli-003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-003-ac2">
        The promotion-candidate list MUST sort claims by descending frequency of
        occurrence multiplied by failure rate, so high-impact candidates surface
        first.
        <trace>fr-cli-003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-cli-003-ac3">
        arc eval audit MUST be read-only relative to scenarios and assertions —
        it MUST NOT modify evals/scenarios/*.md files. Promotion and retirement
        are human-arbitrated actions performed manually after reviewing the audit.
        <trace>fr-cli-003</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
