<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="dashboard">
  <title>Dashboard Consolidation and UI Redesign</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>scripts/eval-dashboard.js (current SSE server)</artifact>
    <artifact>scripts/eval-dashboard-ui.html (current single-pane UI)</artifact>
    <artifact>skill-creator's eval-viewer/viewer.html (reference only, not imported)</artifact>
    <artifact>evals/results/ (trial outputs read at render time)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>skills/arc-evaluating/dashboard/server.js (or equivalent entry point after migration)</artifact>
    <artifact>skills/arc-evaluating/dashboard/ui.html with 2-tab layout, feedback textboxes, keyboard nav</artifact>
    <artifact>evals/results/&lt;scenario&gt;/&lt;runId&gt;/feedback.json (auto-saved human notes)</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-dash-001">
    <title>Two-Tab Layout: Outputs and Benchmark</title>
    <description>
      The dashboard UI MUST present two top-level tabs: "Outputs" and "Benchmark".
      Outputs shows one trial at a time with its prompt, the agent's output files
      rendered inline, grading results, and (when present) a previous-iteration
      side-by-side diff. Benchmark shows aggregate stats: pass rate (mean ±
      stddev), delta, CI, token and duration deltas, and per-assertion breakdown.
      Tab state MUST persist via URL fragment so a user can link a specific
      tab / trial.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-001-ac1">
        Given the dashboard is open on a completed run, clicking the Outputs tab
        MUST render one trial and clicking Benchmark MUST render aggregate stats
        without a page reload.
        <trace>fr-dash-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-001-ac2">
        The active tab and active trial ID MUST be encoded in the URL (e.g.,
        #tab=outputs&amp;trial=3) so copy-pasted URLs open the same view.
        <trace>fr-dash-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-001-ac3">
        The Benchmark tab MUST display token and duration deltas alongside
        pass-rate delta (consuming the data surfaced per fr-gr-002).
        <trace>fr-dash-001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-dash-002">
    <title>Auto-Saving Feedback Textbox per Eval</title>
    <description>
      The Outputs tab MUST include a textbox where the human reviewer can type
      free-form feedback on the displayed trial. Changes MUST be auto-saved to
      evals/results/&lt;scenario&gt;/&lt;runId&gt;/feedback.json within 2 seconds of
      typing stopping. Reloading the page MUST restore the prior feedback. A
      visible status indicator (e.g., "Saved" / "Saving…") SHOULD surface the
      auto-save state.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-002-ac1">
        Given the user types in the feedback textbox and pauses for 2 seconds,
        the content MUST be written to feedback.json at the canonical location
        keyed by trial id.
        <trace>fr-dash-002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-002-ac2">
        Given a trial has prior feedback in feedback.json, navigating to that
        trial MUST pre-populate the textbox with the stored content.
        <trace>fr-dash-002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-002-ac3">
        The UI MUST surface save state so the user is not left guessing whether
        their input persisted. Minimum: a textual indicator that transitions
        between "Saving…" and "Saved" within the save window.
        <trace>fr-dash-002</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-dash-003">
    <title>Keyboard Navigation Between Trials</title>
    <description>
      While the Outputs tab is active, pressing ArrowRight MUST advance to the
      next trial and ArrowLeft MUST go to the previous. The keystrokes MUST NOT
      consume focus when the user is typing in the feedback textbox. Tab order
      MUST remain usable for screen readers; keyboard shortcuts are additive,
      not exclusive.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-003-ac1">
        Given the Outputs tab is active and the cursor is outside any input, a
        single ArrowRight press MUST render the next trial in sequence.
        <trace>fr-dash-003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-003-ac2">
        Given the cursor is inside the feedback textbox, ArrowLeft / ArrowRight
        MUST move the cursor within the text, NOT navigate trials.
        <trace>fr-dash-003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-003-ac3">
        At the first or last trial respectively, ArrowLeft / ArrowRight MUST be
        a no-op (no wrap-around, no error).
        <trace>fr-dash-003</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-dash-004">
    <title>Retain SSE Real-Time Monitoring</title>
    <description>
      The SSE channel from the current dashboard MUST be preserved in the
      consolidated UI. While an eval run is in progress, in-flight trial
      progress MUST appear on the Outputs tab without a page reload. The
      real-time capability differentiates arcforge's dashboard from
      skill-creator's static viewer and MUST NOT be lost in the consolidation.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-004-ac1">
        Given an arc eval ab run is in progress, the dashboard MUST display
        newly completed trials within 5 seconds of their completion, without a
        user action.
        <trace>fr-dash-004</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-004-ac2">
        The SSE endpoint (/events or equivalent) MUST remain at a stable URL
        path after the file relocation, so any external tooling that polled the
        prior dashboard continues to work.
        <trace>fr-dash-004</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-dash-004-ac3">
        Given a client disconnects, the server MUST clean up the SSE subscription
        and continue serving other connected clients without leaking memory.
        <trace>fr-dash-004</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
