<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<detail id="grader-pipeline">
  <title>Grader Pipeline Extensions</title>
  <consumes>
    <artifact>scripts/lib/eval.js (trial orchestration)</artifact>
    <artifact>scripts/lib/eval-graders.js (grading dispatch)</artifact>
    <artifact>skills/arc-evaluating/agents/eval-grader.md (model grader prompt)</artifact>
    <artifact>evals/scenarios/*.md (scenario definitions, read-only)</artifact>
  </consumes>
  <produces>
    <artifact>evals/results/&lt;scenario&gt;/&lt;runId&gt;/results.jsonl (with new timing/token fields per trial)</artifact>
    <artifact>evals/results/&lt;scenario&gt;/&lt;runId&gt;/grading.json (with new discovered_claims[] and weak_assertions[] fields)</artifact>
    <artifact>arc eval compare output (with token/time delta columns)</artifact>
  </produces>

  <requirement id="fr-gr-001">
    <title>Capture Per-Trial Timing and Token Metrics</title>
    <description>
      Every trial record in results.jsonl MUST include duration_ms (wall-clock),
      input_tokens, and output_tokens. The harness SHALL capture these at the moment
      the trial completes — this is the only point at which the subagent exit
      notification carries token accounting. Missing any of the three MUST be
      recorded as null (not omitted) so downstream aggregators can distinguish
      "zero" from "not captured".
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-001-ac1">
        Given any completed trial, its results.jsonl entry MUST contain the keys
        duration_ms, input_tokens, output_tokens. A value of null is allowed; a
        missing key is NOT.
        <trace>fr-gr-001</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-001-ac2">
        Given a trial that exits abnormally (timeout, crash), the harness MUST still
        write the partial record with duration_ms measured and the token fields set
        to null. The trial MUST still count toward k for verdict purposes.
        <trace>fr-gr-001</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-gr-002">
    <title>Surface Token and Duration Deltas in Benchmark Reports</title>
    <description>
      The arc eval compare and arc eval report outputs MUST expose aggregated
      duration and token metrics alongside the pass-rate delta. For A/B runs, the
      delta SHOULD be presented as treatment mean minus baseline mean for each of
      duration_ms, input_tokens, output_tokens. This makes it visible when a skill
      improves quality but doubles cost — a regression that pass rate alone cannot catch.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-002-ac1">
        Given a completed A/B run with timing and token data, arc eval compare MUST
        print duration_ms delta, input_tokens delta, and output_tokens delta in its
        summary section, in addition to assertion pass-rate delta.
        <trace>fr-gr-002</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-002-ac2">
        Given any delta in tokens or duration exceeding 100% (treatment doubles
        baseline), the compare output MUST visually mark it (flag, warning symbol,
        or equivalent) so the cost regression is not overlooked.
        <trace>fr-gr-002</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-gr-003">
    <title>discovered_claims[] Field in grading.json</title>
    <description>
      The eval-grader agent MUST populate a discovered_claims[] array on grading.json
      for every trial. Each entry MUST have the shape { text, category, passed,
      evidence } where category is one of "factual" | "process" | "quality".
      Discovered claims are extracted from the output beyond the predefined
      assertions. They MUST NOT count toward the pass rate used by the verdict
      layer — they are advisory only, consumed downstream by arc eval audit.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-003-ac1">
        Given a model-graded trial, grading.json MUST contain a discovered_claims[]
        array, possibly empty when the grader found no additional claims worth flagging.
        <trace>fr-gr-003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-003-ac2">
        Given any discovered claim fails, the overall trial pass rate computed by
        the harness MUST be unchanged relative to the same grading.json with an
        empty discovered_claims[]. The pass rate depends only on the predefined
        expectations.
        <trace>fr-gr-003</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-003-ac3">
        Each discovered claim entry MUST include the required keys text, category,
        passed, evidence. Missing keys MUST fail grading.json schema lint.
        <trace>fr-gr-003</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-gr-004">
    <title>weak_assertions[] Field in grading.json</title>
    <description>
      The eval-grader agent MUST populate a weak_assertions[] array on grading.json
      identifying predefined assertions the grader judges to be non-discriminative,
      ambiguous, or unverifiable from the available evidence. Each entry MUST
      reference the assertion id and include a "reason" explanation. These critiques
      MUST NOT affect the current trial's verdict — they are aggregated cross-trial
      by arc eval audit to suggest assertion improvements.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-004-ac1">
        Given a grading pass, grading.json MUST include a weak_assertions[] array
        (possibly empty). Each entry MUST carry at minimum { assertion_id, reason }.
        <trace>fr-gr-004</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-004-ac2">
        Presence or absence of weak_assertions entries MUST NOT change the verdict
        verdict computation — the same trial graded twice with identical expectation
        scores but different weak_assertions MUST yield the same verdict.
        <trace>fr-gr-004</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>

  <requirement id="fr-gr-005">
    <title>Blind-Comparator Auto-Trigger Rule</title>
    <description>
      The harness MUST auto-invoke the eval-blind-comparator as a supplementary
      signal after the main A/B comparison if and only if ALL predefined assertions
      in the scenario are model-graded. Mixed grading (any code-graded assertion
      present) MUST suppress the blind run. Code-only scenarios MUST NOT invoke
      blind — the signal adds no value when assertions are deterministic.
    </description>
    <acceptance_criteria>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-005-ac1">
        Given a scenario whose assertions are all model-graded, arc eval ab MUST
        invoke the blind-comparator after the main grading completes and attach
        its preference-rate output to the report.
        <trace>fr-gr-005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-005-ac2">
        Given a scenario that mixes code-graded and model-graded assertions, arc
        eval ab MUST NOT invoke the blind-comparator. The report MUST still show
        the main delta plus a note stating blind was skipped due to mixed grading.
        <trace>fr-gr-005</trace>
      </criterion>
      <criterion id="fr-gr-005-ac3">
        Given a scenario whose assertions are all code-graded, arc eval ab MUST
        NOT invoke the blind-comparator. The report MUST NOT mention blind at all.
        <trace>fr-gr-005</trace>
      </criterion>
    </acceptance_criteria>
  </requirement>
</detail>
